<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE document [
<!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
]>

<document
  title="JPivot"
  version="@VERSION@"
>

<section title="JPivot">

  <page title="Home" id="index">

    JPivot is a JSP custom tag library that renders an OLAP table and let users
    perform typical OLAP navigations like slice and dice, drill down and roll up.
    It uses <a href="http://mondrian.sourceforge.net">Mondrian</a> as its OLAP Server.
    JPivot also supports <a href="http://www.xmla.org">XMLA</a> datasource access.

    <h3>How to run?</h3>
    Download the <tt>jpivot-[version].zip</tt> and extract the <tt>jpivot.war</tt> file.
    Place the war file into tomcats webapp directory.
    <p />
    Make sure, Mondrian gets some memory for caching - this will improve speed
    significantly. For example, set the environment variable
    <code>
      JAVA_OPTS=-Xms256m -Xmx512m
    </code>
    to have 256 megs for caching and 512 megs for temporary peaks.
    <p />
    Start Tomcat and point your browser to <a href="http://localhost:8080/jpivot">http://localhost:8080/jpivot</a>.
    You'll need JDK 1.4 and Tomcat 4.1.30, JPivot does not work with earlier versions (sorry).
    <p />
    There are some simple examples that run without a database, but you probably want to
    run the DB examples too.
    Download the <a href="http://sourceforge.net/project/showfiles.php?group_id=35302&amp;package_id=55863">Mondrian Data</a>
    and set up an ODBC datasource called <tt>MondrianFoodMart</tt> that uses MS Access
    Database and points to <tt>MondrianFoodMart.mdb</tt> from the above download.
    JPivot examples are configured to use this setup.

    <h4>Using JDBC driver</h4>
    JPivot reads the connection parameters from JSPs
    containing the &lt;jp:mondrianQuery ...&gt; tag which contains the MDX query. This allows to
    run queries against different databases. The example JSPs live in /WEB-INF/queries
    and are configured for MS Access, the MySQL version is commented out. You will have
    to change these to run other databases.

    <h4>Using J2EE DataSource</h4>
    You may use a predefined JDBC DataSource to run your MDX queries.
    <pre>
    &lt;jp:mondrianQuery
       id="query01"
       dataSource="jdbc/JPivotDS"
       catalogUri="/WEB-INF/demo/FoodMart.xml"&gt;
        MDX goes here
    &lt;/jp:mondrianQuery&gt;
    </pre>
    Look at the tomcat documentation to see how to set up a datasource. Example follows:
    <pre>
    &lt;Context path="/jpivot" docBase="C:\dev\jpivot\build\web" debug="0"
             reloadable="true" crossContext="true"&gt;
      &lt;Resource auth="Container" name="jdbc/JPivotDS"
          type="javax.sql.DataSource"/&gt;
      &lt;ResourceParams name="jdbc/JPivotDS"&gt;
        &lt;parameter&gt;
          &lt;name&gt;factory&lt;/name&gt;
          &lt;value&gt;org.apache.commons.dbcp.BasicDataSourceFactory&lt;/value&gt;
        &lt;/parameter&gt;
        &lt;parameter&gt;
          &lt;name&gt;maxActive&lt;/name&gt;
          &lt;value&gt;400&lt;/value&gt;
        &lt;/parameter&gt;
        &lt;parameter&gt;
          &lt;name&gt;maxWait&lt;/name&gt;
          &lt;value&gt;5000&lt;/value&gt;
        &lt;/parameter&gt;
        &lt;parameter&gt;
          &lt;name&gt;maxIdle&lt;/name&gt;
          &lt;value&gt;2&lt;/value&gt;
        &lt;/parameter&gt;
        &lt;parameter&gt;
          &lt;name&gt;username&lt;/name&gt;
          &lt;value&gt;tarzan&lt;/value&gt;
        &lt;/parameter&gt;
        &lt;parameter&gt;
          &lt;name&gt;password&lt;/name&gt;
          &lt;value&gt;jane&lt;/value&gt;
        &lt;/parameter&gt;
        &lt;parameter&gt;
          &lt;name&gt;driverClassName&lt;/name&gt;
          &lt;value&gt;com.mysql.jdbc.Driver&lt;/value&gt;
        &lt;/parameter&gt;
        &lt;parameter&gt;
          &lt;name&gt;url&lt;/name&gt;
          &lt;value&gt;jdbc:mysql://localhost:3306/foodmart?autoReconnect=true&lt;/value&gt;
        &lt;/parameter&gt;
      &lt;/ResourceParams&gt;
    &lt;/Context&gt;
    </pre>

    In web.xml you have to reference the data source as follows:
    <pre>
    &lt;resource-ref&gt;
      &lt;description&gt;DB Connection&lt;/description&gt;
      &lt;res-ref-name&gt;jdbc/JPivotDS&lt;/res-ref-name&gt;
      &lt;res-type&gt;javax.sql.DataSource&lt;/res-type&gt;
      &lt;res-auth&gt;Container&lt;/res-auth&gt;
    &lt;/resource-ref&gt;
    </pre>

    <h3>How to compile?</h3>
    The distribution contains binary and source. The jpivot.war file contains in its /WEB-INF/lib
    directory all *.jar files that are needed to build. The simplest way to set up a build environment
    is to
    <ol>
      <li>extract the jpivot.war file to some temp directory by renaming it to jpivot.zip </li>
      <li>from /WEB-INF/lib copy all *.jar files <em>except jpivot.jar</em> to the lib/ directory
       of the jpivot distribution (which already contains mondrian-src.jar</li>
    </ol>
    Now you should be able to build JPivot using ant. You will have to
    define the following ant properties in your build.properties (e.g. in your home directory):
    <code><pre>
    catalina.home=c:/java/jakarta-tomcat-4.1.30
    mysql.home=c:/java/mysql-connector-java-3.0.8-stable
    xalan.home=c:/java/xalan-j_2_6_0
    </pre></code>
    Then ant should work. For running the tests you will have to set up the
    MondrianFoodMart database, either MS Access or MySQL (see build.xml).

    <h3>How to use in another web application?</h3>
    Unzip the war file. You will need the following files
    <ul>
      <li>/wcf/**</li>
      <li>/jpivot/**</li>
      <li>/WEB-INF/wcf/**</li>
      <li>/WEB-INF/jpivot/**</li>
      <li>/WEB-INF/lib/**</li>
      <li>You will have to merge the entries from /WEB-INF/web.xml into your applications web.xml</li>
    </ul>

  </page>




 <page title="Architecture Overview">

JPivot is designed to work with several OLAP servers, especially XMLA and
Mondrian. So JPivot does not use the Mondrian API directly. It defines its
own OLAP model in terms of interfaces in the packages
<a href="api/com/tonbeller/jpivot/olap/model/package-summary.html">olap.model</a>
and
<a href="api/com/tonbeller/jpivot/olap/navi/package-summary.html">olap.navi</a>.
To make JPivot work with Mondrian
these interfaces have to be implemented using Mondrian classes.

   <p/>

JPivot uses WCF (Web Component Framework) packages that support building UI components
via XML and XSLT.

</page>


 <page title="Changelog" id="changelog">
   <h2>New in version 1.4</h2>
   <ul>
     <li>Runs with BEA now (most likely)</li>
     <li>Open CVS</li>
     <li>Many more WCF Tests available</li>
   </ul>

   <h2>New in version 1.3</h2>
   <ul>
     <li>native XMLA access, i.e. no Mondrian required</li>
     <li>Mondrian: Error message on resultset overflow: when the resultset exceeds some limit defined
         in mondrian.properties, an error message is displayed and the previous state is restored.
         default is mondrian.result.limit=50000</li>
     <li>Mondrian: new formatter attributes allows to format members and cells via java code</li>
     <li>Mondrian: other improvements, removed CachePool (it did not do anything useful), made
         SmartMemberReader the default (ignores largeDimensionThreasHold)</li>
     <li>wcf improvements and new features, including sql tables</li>
   </ul>

   <h2>New in version 1.2.1</h2>
   <h3>PDF Improvements</h3>
   Bugfix &amp; more options from Print Property dialog are supported

   <h3>Mondrian Improvements</h3>
   NON EMPTY Crossjoin optimization included. Crossjoin of large sparsed
   sets resulted in OutOfMemoryException before.


   <h2>New in version 1.2.0</h2>
    <h3>Excel and PDF Support</h3>
        contributed Excel/PDF by Ati (uramisten) - thanks a lot.
        Includes other fixes too, see
        <a href="http://sourceforge.net/forum/message.php?msg_id=2590176">forum</a>.

    <h3>OLAP Navigator</h3>
        The navigator now groups large amounts of Members,
        e.g. the custmer names in the foodmart example.
    <h3>Integration with JavaServer Faces</h3>
        WFC (and JPivot) interoperate with
        <a href="http://java.sun.com/j2ee/javaserverfaces/overview.html">JavaServer Faces</a>.
        See examples in WCF download for details.

    <h3>EL Syntax changed</h3>
        The Syntax of the WCF Expression Language (actually its based on
        jakarta BeanUtils) has changed from <tt>${expr}</tt> to
        <tt>#{expr}</tt> so it cooperates from the expression language
        available in Tomcat 5 / JSP 2.0.
        <p />
        So with JSP 2.0 you should use <code>#{}</code> notation to define
        expressions for WCF attributes and <code>${}</code> to define
        JSP EL expressions.
        <p />
        JSP EL expressions can not be used with WCF tags currently, all
        tag attributes have their <code>rtexprvalue</code> set to false.
        There may be a twin library supporting JSP EL expressions in
        the future (similar to the twin libraries in JSTL, e.g. core
        and core_rt).

    <h3>Static accessor for RequestContext</h3>
      RequestContext has a static <tt>instance()</tt> method that returns
          the current instance (using java.lang.ThreadLocal). This seems to
          be safe since JSF uses this mechanism too

    <h3>actionReference in XML form descriptions</h3>
    Form handling has been simplified, see example. In the XML file
          describing the HTML form, the &lt;button ...&gt; element
          accepts an element named "actionReference". The value of this
          attribute is interpreted as the name of a function, which
          is called when the user presses the button. The signature of
          the function is <tt>void foo(RequestContext context) throws Exception;</tt>

    <h2>New in version 1.1.0</h2>

    <h3>Mondrian improvements</h3>

    Uses the up-to-date Mondrian version with many bugfixes and improvements:
    <ul>
      <li>uses less memory (only needs 1/5 of previous Mondrian versions)</li>
      <li>Mondrian is 2 times upto 20 times faster depending on the query. Most speed
          improvement when using <tt>aggregate</tt></li>
      <li>new caching strategy - new cache keeps as much items as possible in memory</li>
    </ul>
    See installation notes about how to set the JVM parameters -Xms and -Xmx.

    <h3>New navigation Code</h3>
    The new navigation code fixes some bugs and shortcomings. Also it reduces
    dependencies to mondrian. So with  the new navigation code it should be
    easier to support other OLAP servers like XMLA and JOLAP.

    <h3>Drill Thru</h3>
    Individual Columns maybe selected in drill-thru table.

    <h3>Bookmark Support</h3>
    com.tonbeller.wcf.bookmark.BookmarkManger has static Methods to collect and
    restore the state of all objects in the session. Support is provided for
    the query with its navigations, the table settings and chart via its configuration
    dialog. All properties from configuration dialogs may be stored in a bookmark
    if the <tt>bookmark</tt> attribute of the &lt;wcf:form...&gt; tag is set
    to true.

    <h3>Parameter Support</h3>

    MDX Parameter may be passed as HTTP Parameters. The new JPivot
    tag <tt>clickable</tt> is nested inside the <tt>table</tt> tag
    and specifies a dimension, level or single member that shall be clickable (i.e.
    members are rendered with hyperlinks). The <tt>setParam</tt>
    tag maybe used to extract the HTTP parameter, parse its
    value and update a parameter of the MDX query. Finally
    its possible to display the current parameter values
    via JSTL tags. See jpivot taglib docs and example in test subdirectory
    for details.

    <h2>Version 1.0.2</h2>
    <h3>Charting Support</h3>

    Robin has integrated jfreechart into jpivot with
    support for many different chart styles (bar chart, pie chart etc, 2D 3D).
    There is also a dialog to configure the chart. See screenshots for an
    example.

    <h3>Drill Thru support</h3>
    Does not seem to work with MS Access?

   <h3>Member Properties</h3>

   JPivot supports member properties now. There is a toolbar button that enables / disables
   display of properties in the table. Also there are a few predefined properties that
   are rendered in a special manner:
   <table border="1">
     <tr>
       <th>Name</th>
       <th>Value</th>
       <th>Description</th>
     </tr>
     <tr>
       <td>style</td>
       <td>red|green|yellow</td>
       <td>renders the Member in that color</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
       <td>link</td>
       <td>an url</td>
       <td>creates a hyperlink on the member</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
       <td>arrow</td>
       <td>up|down|blank</td>
       <td>paints an arrow image</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
       <td>image</td>
       <td>an uri. If the uri starts with "/" the context name will be prepended</td>
       <td>paints image</td>
     </tr>
   </table>

   <h3>Tag Library Documentation</h3>
   All WCF and jpivot tags have been documented (see table of contents on the left).

 </page>

 <page title="XML/A">
    <h3>How to access XMLA data sources?</h3>
    Use the <code>xmlaQuery</code> tag instead of <code>mondrianQuery</code>. You will have to
    enter the XMLA URI and a catalog name.<br/>
    <h4>Example</h4>
    <pre>
    &lt;jp:xmlaQuery
       id="query01"
       uri="http://MYSERVER/XML4A/msxisapi.dll"
       catalog="Foodmart 2000"&gt;
        select {[Measures].[Unit Sales]} on columns,
        [Product].[All Products].children on rows
        from Sales where ([Time].[1997])
    &lt;/jp:xmlaQuery&gt;
    </pre>
 </page>

  <page title="Screenshots">
<h3>Axis in hierarchical mode</h3>
<img src="images/jpivot-01.png"/>

<h3>Axis showing the parents of the members</h3>
<img src="images/jpivot-02.png"/>

<h3>Axis in Level Mode</h3>
This is useful, when the result ist sorted in <em>break hierarchy</em> mode.
<p/>
<img src="images/jpivot-03.png"/>


<h3>Sort options</h3>
<img src="images/jpivot-07.png"/>

<h3>Map hierarchies to table axes</h3>
<img src="images/jpivot-04.png"/>

<h3>Select members from a hierarchy for an axis</h3>
<img src="images/jpivot-05.png"/>

<h3>Select members from a hierarchy for the slicer</h3>
<img src="images/jpivot-06.png"/>

<h3>Example with Member Properties</h3>
<img src="images/jpivot-08.png"/>

<h3>Example with Mondrian Foodmart Data</h3>
<img src="images/jpivot-09.png"/>

<h3>Example Chart with Mondrian Foodmart Data</h3>
<img src="images/jpivot-10.png"/>

<h3>Chart Configuration Dialog</h3>
<img src="images/jpivot-12.png"/>

<h3>MDX Edit Form</h3>
<img src="images/jpivot-11.png"/>

  </page>

  <page title="Contribute" id="contribute">
    There is a public CVS at sourceforge. Before you will get comitter access to the CVS I'd like to
    review your first contributions to make sure everything fits together.
    <p />
    Some guidelines
    <ul>
      <li>Never check-in anything before all tests pass.</li>

      <li>Try to avoid modifying existing sources. JPivot is in production use on several sites and the users
      expect things to work the same way in the next release. If you add functionality, add it
      on top, maybe put into a new package, make it optional (so the code compiles without the new package).</li>

      <li>Do not introduce new package dependencies. There are plans to separate the model
      packages (Mondrian, XMLA) from the GUI packages, for example.</li>

      <li>For indentation use 2 blanks, no tabs. This makes the CVS diffs easier to read</li>
    </ul>

  </page>
  <link href="http://cvs.sourceforge.net/viewcvs.py/*checkout*/jpivot/jpivot/src/docs/roadmap.html" title="Roadmap"/>

  <link href="wcf/index.html" title="WCF"/>
  <link href="junit/index.html" title="Unit Tests"/>
  <link href="api/index.html" title="Java Doc"/>
  <link href="tags/jpivot-tags-en.html" title="JPivot Tags"/>
  <link href="tags/wcf-tags-en.html" title="WCF Tags"/>
  <link href="mondrian-schema/index.html" title="Mondrian Schema Plugin"/>

  <link href="http://sourceforge.net/projects/jpivot" title="Project Page"/>
</section>


</document>
